Guide to the Bella C. Landauer Writings and Reference Collection Ca. 1856 - 1972 (bulk 1926-1950) PR 149
New-York Historical Society
Bella C. Landauer Writings and Reference Collection
ca. 1856-1972 (bulk 1926-1950)]
New-York Historical Society
PR 149
12.27 Linear feet (19 boxes)
Scrapbooks, indices, monographs, articles, and correspondence comprise an archive for the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera at the New-York Historical Society as well as for other collections of Landauer's that she deposited at other institutions.
Provenance
Gift of Bella C. Landauer, 1926-1960, with later additions by her son, James D. Landauer.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying will be undertaken by staff only, and is limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day.
Biographical Note
Bella Landauer was born Bella Clara Fackenthal in New York in 1874, the only child of a profitable corset manufacturer. She attended classes at Miss Hewitt's, and became proficient in several foreign languages. Her father disapproved of college for women, so Bella educated herself with her inquiring mind and interest in many different subjects, including opera and theater. In 1900 she married Ian Nathan Landauer, a fabric importer and salesman, and a first-generation immigrant from Germany. The Landauers' sons were born in 1902 and 1906, and Bella devoted her intense energy to the task wife and motherhood. During World War I Mrs. Landauer volunteered for the New York chapter of the American Volunteer Field Service, which took a toll on her health. A doctor ordered her to rest, and Landauer looked to find more suitable activities for herself.
Bella Landauer first began collecting ephemera in 1923, when she bought a portfolio of bookplates and other prints for one hundred dollars. Though that portfolio was later revealed to have been stolen from a dealer, Landauer was permanently hooked on the idea of collecting printed ephemera. She first embarked on a quest to discover and acquire new bookplates. The next year she added tradecards. Subsequently, as she encountered new genres of material, her interests expanded and her collections grew. She traveled to Europe in search of ephemera, and began to create special collections on specific advertising themes.
In 1926, when Landauer moved from her brownstone at 11 West 74th Street into an apartment in the Drake Hotel, she no longer had space to house her already quite large collection of ephemera. She offered part of her collection to the New-York Historical Society, initially presenting a group of trade cards and bookplates, but never stopped adding to and expanding the collection. Landauer was first given a former kitchen in which to store and organize her collections. However, when the Society's building was expanded in the late 1930s, a special room was created on the third floor to house the Landauer Collection.
Landauer was made an Honorary Curator of the collection but was never on the Society's payroll. She spent hours at the Society organizing her various materials, and members of the public were invited to view them on Sunday afternoons. Landauer continued to collect and donate items, including lottery tickets, posters, sheet music, cameo cards, and matchbooks, until her death in 1960. Her son James D. Landauer donated more items to her collections.
Landauer often referred to her collections as "scraps of old paper," but these ephemeral items have proven to be valuable graphic records of their times. The New-York Historical Society's Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera holds over eight hundred thousand items. Landauer also donated ephemera to many other institutions: The Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Smithsonian Institution, the New York Public Library, Dartmouth College library, Library of Congress, and Baker Library at Harvard University.
In 2001, Landauer's reference materials were separated from the ephemera collection material, and PR 149 was created. All three-dimensional items (such as milk cartons, matchbooks, and paperweights) were transferred to the New-York Historical Society's Department of Painting, Sculpture, and Decorative Arts, with the remainder of the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 031) left intact and continuing to be administered by the Society's Library.
General note
Sources:
Missing Title
Black, Mary. American Advertising Posters of the Nineteenth Century from the Bella C. Landauer Collection of the New-York Historical Society. New York: Dover Publications, Inc., 1976.
Landauer, Bella C. "Collecting and Recollecting." New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin. Vol. XLIII, No. 3, July 1959. Pp. 335-349.
Shadwell, Wendy. "Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Art at the New-York Historical Society." in Cameo Cards and Bella C. Landauer. Schoharie, NY: The Ephemera Society of America, 1992.
Scope and Content Note
The Bella C. Landauer Writings and Reference Collection spans the period from 1856 to 1972 and serves as a reference archive for the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 031), as well as for some material in collections that she deposited at other institutions. The collection is divided into six series: Collection Guides and Indices; Correspondence; Publications; Scrapbooks; Reference Works; and Papers of Aerial Advertising Inc. Many items in this collection are published monographs, meant to highlight ephemera from Landauer's collections. Landauer also compiled detailed indices in order to make her collections accessible to researchers (and perhaps to Landauer herself.) They have been separately cataloged, according to Library of Congress classification, into the New-York Historical Society's library catalog and are listed here but not fully described.
Each series is further described int he container listing.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series.
Missing Title
Series I. Collection Guides and Indices
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Publications
Series IV. Scrapbooks
Series V. Reference Works
Series VI. Papers of Aerial Advertising Inc.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Phootgraphs, and Architecture at the New-York Historical Society
The Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 031) at the New-York Historical Society is the reference point for most of the material in this collection. Landauer also donated ephemera to many other institutions. The Metropolitan Museum of Art, National Air and Space Museum at the Smithsonian Institution, New York Public Library, Dartmouth College library, Library of Congress, and Baker Library at Harvard University all hold Landauer collections.
Printed ephemera -- Collectors and collecting.; Advertising -- United States.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Scrapbooks.; Collectors and collecting; Trade catalogs; Correspondence.; Trade cards.; Ephemera.; Photographic prints.; Allen, Reginald; Johnson, John de Monins, 1882-1956
- Series I: Collection Guides and Indices
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes Landauer's various efforts to keep records of her growing collection. She grouped and listed items by their physical location, by type of media, or by subject. This series is composed of three subseries: Bound catalogs, Card catalogs, and Notebook catalogs.
  - Subseries I: Bound Catalogs
    This subseries is sixteen typescript and manuscript catalogs, bound into hard covers with embossed titles. Some of these are guides to different types of ephemera in Landauer's collection ("fans," for example) and some are lists by location in the New-York Historical Society. These catalogs no longer provide accurate access to the collection but show how Landauer managed her collection. Several of the catalogs ("Some Theater," for example) also include lists of ephemera in Landauer collections not at the New-York Historical Society. Catalogs are grouped into those organized by general themes, those organized by type of media, and those providing indices by location, and are thereunder organized alphabetically.
    Two catalogs are organized by general themes. "Interiors" is further titled "Interior Views in the Landauer Collection" and is a manuscript list, alphabetical by subject, with locations provided under each entry. "Some Theater" is largely a typescript inventory by subject, with manuscript additions and a typescript explanation of the organizational method used. Landauer includes "[Theater] Programs at Dartmouth" as a separate heading.
    Most collection catalogs are organized by media format. The titles accurately reflect the list of contents. "Boxes, Glasses, Bottles" is a manuscript list by subject of these three-dimensional items (these materials are now part of the New-York Historical Society's Museum.) "Funnies, Calendars, Artists, Director[ies]" also includes a list of Christmas Cards. This catalog is extra-illustrated with colored trade cards, bubble gum comic wrappers, clippings, and other ephemera relating to the subjects listed within. "Menus" and "Paperweights, Fans" are manuscript list by subject of each format. "Photostats, Photographs, Fans" contains a typewritten and manuscript list of "Material from the Landauer collection that has been photographed" with accompanying New-York Historical Society negative numbers. Several catalog cards with the negative numbers for specific items have been pasted in. Other photographed items are listed by subject with no negative numbers recorded. The listing of fans in this catalog is a duplicate of that in the previous catalog.
    Five catalogs are lists of sheet music by topic. "Beverages" is further titled "Catalogue of Beverage Music, Boxes I and II" and is an alphabetical manuscript list of song titles like "Fill a glass with golden wine" and "I married the bootlegger's daughter." "Dance, Press Music" includes a manuscript listing of sheet music related to dancing or specific dance steps, as well as those with references to newspapers or magazines. In addition, it contains list of music sheets which mentions the comics, and which are related to the Western United States. "Firemen, Panama Canal, U.S. Presidents" is a manuscript listing of music relating to those topics. Unsuccessful presidential nominees are included under the "U.S. Presidents" heading. "New York Music" is a manuscript listing by subject of titles relating to New York City. Landauer has included references to her publications on music titles and to other collections of New York-related sheet music. "War Sheet Music" is a manuscript list arranged alphabetically by title.
    Four catalogs list collection items based on their location. "Corridor list" is a manuscript list by subject of items that were stored in the corridor outside Mrs. Landauer's room at the New-York Historical Society. It is unclear whether these items were stored in frames on the wall or in a display case. "Fashions and Office" includes a manuscript listing by subject of "Materials framed or hanging on wall in Landauer Room" and an item list of "Landauer Material in the Fashion Room." "Table List, Left" is a manuscript listing of "Posters in large table" in drawers on the left side of the table. Posters were foldered by subject; this is an individual title listing. "Table List, Right, Big Case" is a manuscript listing of posters found in drawers on the right side of the table. Oversize posters were found in the "Big Case" and are listed here as well. A list of "Fashion in Music Box," or sheet music relating to fashion, is also included in this catalog.
    Titles have been transcribed from the spines of the catalogs. In some cases, this title is not a sufficient description, and notes in brackets have been added.
    - Organized by Theme
      - Interiors, undated (Box 16, Folder 73)
      - Some Theatre, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Organized by Type of Ephemera
      - Boxes, Glasses, Bottles, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Funnies, Calendars, Artists, Director[ies], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
        General note
        [includes Christmas Cards]
      - Menus, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Paperweights, Fans, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Photostats, Photographs, Fans, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Sheet Music--Beverages, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Sheet Music--Dance, Press Music, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
        [includes Comic and Western]
      - Sheet Music--Firemen, Panama Canal, U.S. Presidents, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
        [includes Presidential nominees]
      - Sheet Music--New York Music, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Sheet Music--War Sheet Music, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Organized by Location
      - Corridor List, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Fashions and Office, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Table List, Left, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
        [Lists posters]
      - Table List, Right, Big Case, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
        [Lists posters and sheet music relating to fashion]
  - Subseries II: Card Catalogs
    The Card catalog is another of Mrs. Landauer's access methods for her collections of ephemera. This catalog lists books and trade catalogs in the collection, by subject. The books referred to in this catalog are now accessible through New-York Historical Society's library online catalog.
    - Advertising-Household, undated (Box 4)
    - Insurance-Yukon, undated (Box 5)
  - Subseries III: Notebooks and Collection Records
    This subseries is material from four three-ring binders that comprise a "Catalogue of American Business." This is a handwritten list of business ephemera, alphabetical by subject. A lot of cross-references exist among the four volumes. Typescript lists and business ephemera are pasted in. During processing the pages were removed from these binders and foldered.
    - Catalogue of American Business, A-E, undated (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - Catalogue of American Business, F-O, undated (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
    - Catalogue of American Business, O-R, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Catalogue of American Business, S-Z, undated (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
- Series II: Correspondence
  Series II includes only correspondence received by Bella C. Landauer. In general, her outgoing correspondence does not seem to have been kept. Landauer did not keep files on correspondents, but instead pasted her correspondence into large scrapbook albums, as she did her ephemera collections. Two of these scrapbooks are part of this series. This series also includes three smaller bound volumes in which correspondence, mainly about specific aspects of Landauer's collections, has been bound together or pasted onto bound pages. The volume with a cover title "Scraps - Bella C. Landauer" contains correspondence, mainly about aeronautics and aeronautical ephemera, from 1930 to 1936. Some of these letters are in French from French correspondents. The volume with spine title, "G and S correspondence Reginald Allen" holds correspondence as well as ephemera relating to Reginald Allen and Gilbert and Sullivan. Allen was an arts administrator and a collector of Gilbert and Sullivan ephemera. The correspondence covers the period between 1939-1951 and is mainly related to discussions of Gilbert and Sullivan ephemeral finds. Some fragile material was removed from the title page of this volume and foldered at the time of processing. A third volume with "B. C. L." embossed on the cover is titled "Letters from composers of Walt Whitman Music 1936-1937." It has a photograph of Walt Whitman pasted on the inside cover. Most of the letters are related to the publication of Landauer's book, Leaves of Music by Walt Whitman, from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer (1937), a listing of sheet music related to Whitman or including Whitman verses.
  Landauer did not always segregate or bind her correspondence; much of it can be found scattered throughout the collection scrapbooks, especially when the letter or postcard related to one specific item of ephemera. This aspect makes it difficult to acquire a complete sense of the volume of correspondence she encountered. In general, Landauer did not broadly solicit donations to her collections, preferring to negotiate with her trusted dealers. During World War II, however, she does appear to have sent out letters to a variety of companies that were awarded the Army-Navy "E" Award for high achievement in war production. Landauer requested copies of the companies' award ceremonies programs; several folders of unbound correspondence are replies to her inquiries, sometimes with the award programs enclosed. One folder of miscellaneous letters includes other loose correspondence to Landauer. Unused sheets of Landauer's letterhead and one small spiral notebook of addresses are included in this series.
  - Correspondence Scrapbook A-P (Box 7)
  - Correspondence Scrapbook Q-Z (Box 8)
  - Scraps - Bella C. Landauer [aeronautical correspondence], 1930-1936 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Letters from composers of Walt Whitman Music, 1936-1937 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - G and S [Gilbert and Sullivan] correspondence Reginald Allen, 1939-1951 (Box 9, Folder 25-26)
  - Correspondence about Army-Navy "E" Award, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 27-28)
  - Correspondence about Army-Navy "E" Award (cont.), 1943 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous loose correspondence, undated (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Unused Landauer letterhead, undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - [Address book], undated (Box 10, Folder 32)
- Series III: Publications
  Series III includes many of Bella C. Landauer's published books, articles, and compilations of items culled from her collections. Many of these same publications (as well as others not included here) can also be found in the New-York Historical Society library. Most of the copies found in this collection are extra-illustrated or have notations in Landauer's hand. The series is divided into three subseries: Articles; Monographs; and Compilations. These publications have been individually cataloged into the New-York Historical Society library catalog and can also be accessed through that resource. Thus they are merely listed here, and are not extensively described.
  - Subseries I: Articles
    This subseries includes Landauer's copies of four articles authored by her, mainly for the New-York Historical Society Quarterly. Offprints of the articles, or copies removed from the journal, have been bound into folders along with her original manuscript or typescript for the article. Landauer co-authored an article with Harry B. Weiss, and the entire issue of The Sportsmen's Pilot, where it appeared, can be found here. Two printed copies of "Jumbo's Influence on Advertising or Some Jumbo Trade Cards" are bound in with Landauer's manuscript of the article, along with multiple photostat copies of the illustrations. A hand-annotated typescript of Landauer's autobiographical talk, "Collecting and Recollecting," follows an offprint and a manuscript version of the piece.
    - "Jumbo's Influence on Advertising or Some Jumbo Trade Cards." New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin. Vol. XVIII, No. 3, October 1934. Pp. 43-52. (Box 16, Folder 74)
    - Some Trade Cards with Particular Emphasis on the Currier and Ives Contributions." New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin. Vol. XVII, No. 4, January 1934. Pp. 79-93. (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - "Collecting and Recollecting." New-York Historical Society Quarterly Bulletin. Vol. XLIII, No. 3, July 1959. Pp. 335-349. (Box 10, Folder 34-35)
    - Landauer, Bella C. and Harry B. Weiss. "Matches made in the heavens." The Sportsman Pilot. Vol. X, No. 2, August 1933. Pp. 12-13. (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Subseries II: Monographs
    The subseries includes eighteen of Landauer's published works. These works often highlight particular aspects of ephemera found in her collections, such as Early American Trade Cards. Others focus on more general subjects, such as The Influence of Shakespeare on Advertising. Illustrations for all of these publications are drawn from Landauer's collections and are printed in black and white. Almost all have handwritten additions or hand corrections to typographical mistakes. Two of these works, which are both variations on Some American Billheads, are in an extremely large format, probably so as to reproduce the billheads at their original size. Some Terpsichorean Ephemera has a color frontispiece, a letter pasted in, and additional handwritten notes. Early American Trade Cards from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer includes a foldout color frontispiece. This volume was printed in an edition of 500 and is considered to be rare. It is annotated with New-York Historical Society's negative numbers of several of the tradecards reproduced, as well as their location in Landauer's collection (some of these were "framed on wall.") Leaves of Music by Walt Whitman includes letters to Landauer by fans of Whitman laid in, as well as an engraving of Whitman from an issue of Harper's. Bookplates from the Aeronautica Collection of Bella C. Landauer has other, actual, bookplates pasted in. Chalking the Hat is about railroad passes with some illustrations. Some Ephemeral Portraits of Lincoln and Franklin is extra-illustrated with cartes-de-visite portraits of Lincoln, a French stamp with an image of Franklin, and has correspondence laid in. Upward not Downward! contains ephemera showing 'Cleopatra's Needle,' the Egyptian obelisk in Central Park. Gilbert and Sullivan Influence on American Tradecards is the most extra-illustrated monograph found here. It has numerous bubble gum cards, trade cards, advertisements, and clippings pasted in. The volume also includes two pamphlets containing the dialogue from "H.M.S. Pinafore," one from an 1879 edition of Louis Klopsch's Complete and Unabridged Miniature Librettos.
    - Bookplates from the Aeronautica Collection of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Harbor press, 1930. (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - "Chalking the hat", etc., from the Collections of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Harbor press, 1930. (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Early American Trade Cards from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. New York: W. E. Rudge, 1927. (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Gilbert and Sullivan Influence on American Tradecards, from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Priv. print., 1936. (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Leaves of Music by Walt Whitman, from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Harbor Press, 1937. (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - My City 'tis of Thee; New York City on Sheet-music Covers. Selections from the Music Collection of Bella C. Landauer at the New-York Historical Society. New York: The New-York Historical Society, 1951. (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Printers' Mottoes: a Collection of Sentiments Taken from Title-pages and Colophons of Books Issued by Printers and Publishers, Booksellers, Artists and Patrons from the 15th Century to the Present. New York: Priv. print., 1926. (Box 21, Folder unknown container)
    - Some Aeronautical Music from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. Paris: Priv. Print., 1933. (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Some Alcoholic Americana; from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Harbor press, 1932. (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Some American Billheads from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer at the New-York Historical Society. [New York] c. 1949. [2 copies] (Box 21, Folder unknown container)
    - Some Early American Lottery Items. New York: Harbor Press, 1928. (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Some Early Vermont Invitations from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Harbor Press, 1930. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Some Ephemeral Portraits of Lincoln and Franklin from the Collections of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Harbor Press, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 40)